The most important question you should ask about Cedric Price is why did he die so
soon?
Because I think that he would have been in his element in the smart thinking about
cities and planning that we have available today,
which links back to his thinking about cybernetics, about the way cities work, the
social aspects of cities,
brain power and the ability to analyze things at the speed of light and to be clever
about the way
we do things so I think that I feel sorry that he's not around now to help us
evaluate what is
going on in relationship to new technologies and the way we run our cities yeah when
I saw Cedric
for the first time, yeah, I mean, he was no doubt a star.
You know, he had this rather portly carriage,
always with the cigar puffing away.
And he was somebody who stood out from the rest.
Generally, as I say, with his rounded, stiff, starched collars,
knitted black tie, baggy black jumper and hush puppy shoes, very distinctive and
his own man very much really and that sort of long black hair that he swept
back. He was quite difficult to pin down, he was quite secretive, everyone
thought he didn't have to work because he was the heir to the fortune of the Prices
Candle Factory
fortune but I don't believe that was actually the case. Nevertheless he would
generally drive around
in chauffeur driven cars quite frequently. I at that stage lived in the West Country
in a small
village called Laycock in Wiltshire and he decided to come down and visit my family
for the day and
he took a taxi all the way from London it's about 108 miles actually to get there
taxi all the way
down taxi waited while he had lunch had a look around the village and the taxi took
him back
again so um you know he he lived a fairly luxurious existence in in that way and he
made
really specific choices about how he ran his life obviously lunch eating and
drinking were
a key part of the pleasures he got out of life.
When I was editor of Building Design, for instance,
every Monday morning I would go at 8 o'clock
for what you call breakfast.
Breakfast was a glass of brandy.
His was a bit deeper than mine.
I have to say I was surprised that brandy at that time
in the morning has a very energizing impact on you for quite a long time during the
day,
which is, but I didn't really take to it. Nevertheless, those meetings were another
interesting side of him of his interest in politics, his interest in gossip, his
interest
in the way you had an impact on decision-making at the highest level
and made him really behind the scenes politically very powerful.
To me, he was something of a mystery always.
He was always found tremendously charming,
very charming to the ladies.
and yet there were times when he could react very angrily about things.
I remember the thing that he used to get most upset was
if one turned up at the office without an appointment,
which he only did once,
and he liked things to be organised
and I'm sure many people have told you about East Grinstead
so that he could disappear when he wanted to.
But he never actually taught me
because when I came to the AA, he wasn't teaching here.
But in those days, I always think the AA had a rather better relationship
with practices in the area, in London,
and you could go out and forage for yourself
to find people who would support you.
So he was really a mentor for me, particularly when I was editing Clip Kit with
Jeffrey Smythe.
So Jeffrey and I would go and have regular meetings with Cedric.
And Cedric would be totally generous with his address book and put us in touch with
everybody we needed to talk to
in terms of collecting editorial content,
in terms of distributing or anything we needed.
As long as we had made an appointment before we turned up,
he would then be totally generous with his time.
And that in itself has influenced me completely during my career
because I believe one should...
Every student who rings up and wants half an hour of your time,
you give it because I think that's what he gave to me
and I think that's something you give back as well.
And so I feel there was huge generosity there,
a social generosity in that he was a wonderful raconteur
and party-goer and lunch companion.
I worked very closely with Cedric when I was technical editor at AD,
where we produced a catalogue, really, of his work up until then.
And, you know, like almost everything he did,
you had to go back to first principles about why you were doing something,
how you actually published it,
and then you did something which was a bit different to a normal way of doing it.
All the constraints of publishing were set aside, really.
And also, of course, you set aside the idea that he had any fixed ideas about
things,
because you realise that although he may have done a scheme a couple of years
before,
times would have changed, his own thinking would have changed,
and therefore you had to re-evaluate things
in the context of the time that has elapsed.
So each project that we published,
there would be comments by him that would bring it up to date
and also then comments by me about how I read the situation
and how I interpreted the project.
So there was that element to it.
Nothing was fixed, and to a certain extent, again,
the internet would have been a much better way of publishing his blogs
rather than actually paper was not, in terms of publishing,
the thing that would have been best to describe the shifting attitudes
towards projects he'd only done maybe 12 months before.
That being said, he was a great one for collecting paper.
he loved indexing there was every sheet of paper that he gave you had a whole
complex
list of references and so on so that it could easily be found in the finding system
so
again that was something that you know he would have been very much at home in the
sort of data-driven world we live in today.
And so he liked the organisation of it,
so instead of publishing it as a story or a long article,
everything was very episodic,
everything was in a special gridded system that we set it into,
and everything was referenced with its own numbers
so that, again, they could be filed and you could actually tear the centrepiece out
of the magazine
and you could actually file it into one whole publication.
Poliart was the one I got most involved with in that I totally understood his
frustration
at the sort of skills available in education across the country,
but the inability of students within each school to access those skills available.
Again, this is something which today would be much easier to do with digital media,
but then in a sort of paper-driven teaching base that we had then, it was more
difficult.
So PolyArc was a way of creating a network between schools,
and we got together the PolyArc bus.
The Polyark bus was using a Routemaster.
At that time, London Transport had actually just bought a whole lot of new buses
and it had fields full of very good quality Routemaster buses,
which they sold for, I think they were only about £3,000 you could buy one for then.
The AA bought one and Tony Gwilliam, who was then second year tutor,
actually had one which the students were converting into larger space at the top
with wings that folded out.
So you create a sort of three times the floor area
and a bathroom pod which fitted into the deck at the back of the bus.
And so we borrowed the bus and Dennis Crompton and the communications unit
set up a whole series of videos for us of mainly AA tutors
and of course Cedric as well,
talking about a series of issues.
So we went with these videos.
We got on the bus, drove up.
First stop was Cambridge.
Then we went on up to Nottingham, Edinburgh and so on.
And in each place we unloaded the video kit,
showed people films and videos of AA tutors mainly.
And then we also took videos of the schools that we arrived at
to get their responses to some of the things they'd seen
and also to take messages from one school onto the next.
And so we went up through Nottingham.
Nottingham was a slight problem in that we hit a low bridge,
but luckily the steel structure of the leaves that came out
was so strong that we actually just forced the bus down on its suspension
and skidded under the bridge, but it did knock some of the construction off.
So it wasn't all plain sailing, but it was very instructive
for students who we picked up and then took on to the next school.
So we would pick Cambridge students up, take them to Nottingham, leave them there
and then Nottingham students went on up to Newcastle.
I remember one of the, we took Eric Parry from Newcastle up to Edinburgh and then we
actually got thrown out of Edinburgh
because one of the AA students who was something of a radical was offended by the
fact that we were not able to use their studios
because there was a dance event going on,
and he was Glaswegian,
and there was some tension between Glasgow students
and Edinburgh students.
We were persona non grata in Edinburgh at the time,
although that was where I first met Diane Sujic,
who then later had become editor of Blueprint.
Then we actually went down to Bath
and met a chap who was a great friend of Cedric's.
Again, one of these people he'd introduced us to
who had a wonderful Gothic mansion he was restoring
and had the main concession for repairing Morris Miners in Bath.
Charlie Ware, his name was, who was a great friend of Cedric's.
So we went down to Bath, Bristol, then back up to London again.
So polyarch was then very physical, now would be more digital,
and in fact there is still a sort of polyarch network that continues on today,
exchanging information about school.
So polyarch was interesting and we produced a big chunk of an issue of AD on
polyarch.
Potteries Thinkbelt he was working on that while I was here at the AA and again
you know that continued on all sorts of issues I was interested in which
about temporariness about change about reuse about sustainability
and it brought together so many issues which I think you know have grown in
significance over
the years but which were totally ignored by most of the people teaching architecture
at the time.
Yes, the Potteries Thinkbelt was a project related to the area around Stoke-on-Trent
which had been an area of great industrial growth in the 19th, early 20th century
where pottery was made.
It's an area that Cedric knew well.
There was massive unemployment
and the area was in need of regeneration.
And so he saw education,
the economic salvation of the area,
the knowledge economy, which we know about today,
but was then not something people even spoke about.
So, you know, Frederick was incredibly prescient, really,
in realising that this was a key driver
for economic growth and regeneration.
And then, again, very different to the normal reaction
in those days of you just build buildings
to create regenerative opportunities,
he actually used the existing infrastructure,
redundant rail carriages and so on,
could be moved around, were very flexible,
they made ideal teaching spaces and so the architecture actually became the
network the connection between the main centers within the Potteries Thinkbelt
area which could reuse that infrastructure to deliver a totally
different sort of economy Cedric was influential because he was very canny a
amazing networker and he knew which buttons to press to actually have an
influence on things he was he was very close to senior members of the Labour
Party for instance and he tended to keep a lot of these areas slightly in silos
you didn't meet a lot of the people he mixed with and they party every now and
then you'd bump into them in East Grinstead. But so he, within the Labour movement,
he
had a whole network of people. So if he needed to put a bit of pressure in high
places, he
knew how to do that. He had a very strong social network. He moved in, I mean, just
his connections with Tony Snowdon and people like that,
the fact that he was a regular visitor to Kensington Palace
at the time when Princess Margaret was there
was again a link into a wider society.
Yet then when Prince Charles spoke out about architecture
and was promoting an idea of, I might say,
the antithesis to what Cedric thought the future of architecture was,
he got very upset about that.
And I did actually organise a dinner for the architecture club,
of which I was secretary at the time,
which Cedric was a long-standing member of the architecture club.
He had been a member of the architecture before I was even secretary.
And he would turn up to almost every dinner.
generally in his cups at the end of the dinner
would talk at great length on some esoteric subject
but once we invited the Prince of Wales
to speak at dinner
Cedric never came to another architecture club dinner after that
he was really annoyed and insulted
that we had actually given a platform to the Prince of Wales
so although he moved within those circles
he knew where to draw the line
he was a very social animal
so that he was all around the place
he would be at all the parties
so he knew how to network in a very sophisticated way
and he knew how to use the press as well
he was obviously great friends with Rainer Bannum
when he was writing in New Society
and also with Paul Barker who was editor of New Society
then New Society at that time was a very powerful magazine
and articles like his Non-Plan article
really can have resonance to this day
so he knew how to communicate in that sort of sphere
I used to criticise him really for, he had a fairly obtuse way of using English
which he thought was fine because he felt people needed to make a bit of an effort
to understand what he was saying.
however I do think that did restrict sometimes the breadth of the audience
that he could have garnered if he had really tried. Cedric was about people and
the way that people relate to architecture and his well-known
aphorism that you know when asked about a new house for a couple he said you
don't want a house you need a divorce is something which I'm sure many other people
have repeated to
you but I think nevertheless shows that you actually obtain the solutions that
aren't often
expected of buildings through other means that we are dealing with the way people
lead their lives and the architects knee-jerk response is too often just to
build something to house whatever activity that is whereas he showed us
that there are ways that don't require building that you can actually have the
same impact and I would say that if you look at interaction and what happened
and the fact that meanwhile spaces, pop-ups, temporary use,
all those sorts of things have an impact on the way that cities work
without having to be fixed buildings like the ones around us here.
That influence has been very powerful and I think has shown to be effective.
I think the relevance of Cedric today is actually almost more important because
although he is a powerful figure in the architectural community at the moment,
I feel that we are going through a period where architects are actually producing
more fixed pieces of iconic architecture than at any previous period really.
and that is the antithesis of what Cedric was about.
And I would say that if you look at the world today
in terms of architectural output,
we are building a huge volume of space
that is so constrained by design
that actually we're going to find it very difficult
to actually operate those pieces of kit in the future.
and that we need to actually look at a much freer way of building
and other contemporaries of Cedric like Habrakon for instance
need to be brought into the mix
to look at systems of building that provide greater freedom
and actually look more at the use than the artifact.